Guide to the Disability Access Services Records 1973-2016
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections and Archives Research Center
Disability Access Services Records
1973-2016
1984-1992
Oregon State University. Disability Access Services.
RG 273
1.15 cubic feet, including 84 photographs 3 boxes, including 1 oversize box
Special Collections and Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR, 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2075 Email: scarc@oregonstate.edu Web: http://scarc.library.oregonstate.edu/findingaids
The Disability Access Services Records focus on programs and services provided by the former Services for Students with Disabilities office at Oregon State University, as well as the student organizations, Handicapped Students Unlimited and the Disabled Students Organization. The Disability Access Services Office began as Handicapped Services, located in the Counseling Center, during the late 1970s. In the early 1980s, Handicapped Services became the office of Services for Students with Disabilities (SSD). The office would later be renamed as the Disability Access Services office.
Historical Note:
Efforts to address the needs of students with disabilities attending Oregon State University began in the early 1970s with the formation of the Advisory Committee for Persons with Disabilities. The committee sought to comply with Section 204 of the 1973 Rehabilitation Act, including making buildings increasingly accessible. In 1977, Pamela Walker became the first Coordinator of Services to the Handicapped. The goal of the position was to create a program that provided services for students with disabilities and identified barriers to student success.
The Disability Access Services Office began as Handicapped Services, located in the Counseling Center, during the late 1970s. In the early 1980s, Handicapped Services became the office of Services for Students with Disabilities (SSD). The office was transferred from the Counseling Center to the Office of Student Services, later renamed the Dean of Students Office, in January 1984. During the 1990s, the SSD office would experience two additional moves, first to the Office of Academic Affairs during the Fall of 1994, and later to the Office of Student Affairs during the Fall of 1997. The Services for Students with Disabilities office would later be renamed as the Disability Access Services office.
As the office evolved, new programs and services were introduced to address the growing needs of students, including the Learning Disabilities Program, approved in the mid-1980s, and the Disability Access Services Testing Center, opened in 2012. Student organizations were also founded alongside the programs. The Handicapped Students Unlimited became a recognized student organization in 1976, hosting the first Handicapped Awareness Week in May of 1978. The organization would later be renamed as the Disabled Students Organization.
Oregon State University. Disabled Students Organization.; Oregon State University. Handicapped Students Unlimited.; Oregon State University. Services for Students with Disabilities.
Assistive computer technology.; Clubs--Oregon--Corvallis.; College buildings--Barrier-free design.; College students with disabilities--Oregon--Corvallis.; Learning disabilities.
Colleges and Universities; Clubs and Societies; Student Life; Corvallis; Oregon; Photographs; Scrapbooks
The records were transferred to the former University Archives in 2002 and an addition was received in 2016.
This collection is open for research.
Additional collections documenting programs and policies regarding students and employees with disabilities are the Affirmative Action Office Records (RG 172) and Associated Students of Oregon State University (ASOSU) Records (RG 011). An additional collection documenting student organizations is the Student Club and Organization Records (RG 276).
The Disability Access Services Records are arranged into 4 series: 1. Annual Reports, Funding, and Statistics, 1975-2001; 2. Policies, 1985-1991; 3. Academic Accommodations and Services, 1973-2003; and 4. Programs, Student Organizations, and Committees, 1976-2016.
The Disability Access Services Records primarily contain annual reports and memoranda discussing accessibility on the Oregon State University campus and funding for services and programs. The collection also contains scrapbooks documenting the student organizations, Handicapped Students Unlimited and the Disabled Students Organizations, through newspaper clippings, advertisements, and photographs.
Series one contains annual reports, statistics, and memoranda discussing funding and grant proposals for the Services for Students with Disabilities office. The second series focuses on policies affecting students with disabilities on campus, including discrimination, classroom accessibility, and services for students with learning disabilities.
Series three contains memoranda, student handbooks, and staff guides discussing building accessibility and services provided by the Services for Students with Disabilities office. Series 4 focuses on student organizations and programs, including the Program for Learning Disabilities, Services for Students with Disabilities, and the Disabled Students Organization. The series primarily contains memoranda, articles, and two scrapbooks documenting student organization activities. A series of posters promoting the Disability Accessibility Services office are also included.
- Annual Reports, Funding, and Statistics, 1975-2001; Series 1
  Series 1 contains primarily annual reports and statistics for the Services for Students with Disabilities Program. Memoranda discusses grant proposals and funding for programs and services.
  - Annual Reports and Statistics, 1975-1996 (Box-folder 1.01)
  - Annual Reports and Statistics, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 1.02)
  - Annual Reports and Statistics, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 1.03)
  - Grant Proposals, 1975-1982 (Box-folder 1.04)
  - Program and Services Funding Memoranda, 1977-1989 (Box-folder 1.05)
  - Program and Services Funding Memoranda, 1990-1995 (Box-folder 1.06)
- Policies, 1985-1991; Series 2
  Series 2 contains primarily memoranda and correspondence discussing policies affecting students with disabilities on campus, including admission procedures, classroom accessibility, and services for students with learning disabilities. Additional topics include nondiscrimination policies, honor roll recognition, and concerns regarding a policy restricting disabled students to one service per course.
  - Memoranda and Guidelines, 1985-1991 (Box-folder 1.07)
- Academic Accommodations and Services, 1973-2003; Series 3
  Series 3 focuses on services provided regarding accessibility, priority registration, and alternative testing sites for students with learning disabilities. The series also contains staff guides and student handbooks containing floor plans for campus buildings and accessibility resources.
  - Priority Registration and Scheduling, 1977-1991 (Box-folder 2.01)
  - Building Accessibility and Assistive Technology, 1978-1999 (Box-folder 2.02)
  - Student Services Memoranda and Articles, 1983-1994 (Box-folder 2.03)
  - Alternative Testing, 1985-1991 (Box-folder 2.04)
  - Student Handbooks and Staff Guides, 1973-1996 (Box-folder 2.05)
  - Student Handbooks and Staff Guides, 1998-2003 (Box-folder 2.06)
- Programs, Student Organizations, and Committees, 1976-2016; Series 4
  Series 4 focuses on programs and student organizations on campus, including the Program for Learning Disabilities, Services for Students with Disabilities, and the Disabled Students Organization. Two scrapbooks containing primarily newspaper clippings and photographs document activities of the Disabled Students Organization and Handicapped Students Unlimited. A series of posters promoting the Disability Accessibility Services office are also included.
  - University Advisory Committee for Persons with Disabilities, 1981-1991 (Box-folder 2.07)
  - Services for Students with Disabilities, 1983-1992 (Box-folder 2.08)
  - Program for Learning Disabilities, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 2.09)
  - Program for Learning Disabilities, 1987-1991 (Box-folder 2.10)
  - Disabled Students Organization, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 2.11)
  - State and National Programs, 1978-1983 (Box-folder 2.12)
  - Handicapped Students Unlimited Scrapbook, 1976-1979; 3.01 (Box-item 3.01)
    30 prints
  - Disabled Students Organization Scrapbook, 1986-1993; 3.02 (Box-item 3.02)
    40 prints, 14 negatives, and a contact sheet.
  - Disability Access Services Posters, 2016 (Box-folder 3.01)